A Finding Aid to the Sylvia Shaw Judson Papers, 1911-1975, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Sylvia Shaw Judson papers
1911-1975
Archives of American Art
Haskins, Sylvia Shaw Judson, 1897-1978
AAA.hasksylv
Archival Resource Key
4.3 Linear feet
The papers of sculptor Sylvia Shaw Judson measure 4.3 linear feet and date from 1911 to 1975. Found are biographical materials, correspondence, writings, professional activities files, personal business records, printed material, and photographs of works of art.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1920-1960 (4 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1920-1975 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, 1911-1963 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 4: Professional Activities Files, 1933-1968 (0.6 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Series 5: Personal Business Records, 1923-1975 (0.4 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1913-1970s (0.9 linear feet; Boxes 2-3, OV6)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1920s-circa 1970s (1.9 linear feet; Boxes 3-6, OV7-8, MGP1)
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Scope and Contents
The papers of sculptor Sylvia Shaw Judson measure 4.3 linear feet and date from 1911 to 1975. Found are biographical materials, correspondence, writings, professional activities files, personal business records, printed material, and photographs of works of art.
Biographical materials include resumes and scattered artwork by Judson and others. Correspondence is largely professional and is with artists, galleries, institutions, and museums around the Midwest and the rest of United States. Judson's writings include articles and lectures about art but also include literary writings from her high school years. Material relating to Judson's career as an educator, sculptor, and writer may include research notes, photographs, and business documents. Business records contain receipts and invoices for the production and for the sale of her works. Of note are lists which document the location of her sculptures. Printed materials document Judson's sculpture and art career, and include published books she wrote or illustrated. Photographs are of works of art.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on 35mm microfilm reels 1490-1495 and 4189-4190, at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Separated Materials
The Archives of American Art also holds microfilm of material lent for microfilming on reels 4189-4190, including biographical material, family and personal correspondence primarily between Sylvia Judson and her parents and husband, travel journals, writings, sketchbooks and sketches, printed material, and photos of sculpture study. The material was returned to the lender after microfilming and some was subsequently donated to the Chicago Historical Society. Loaned materials are not described in the collection container inventory.
Biographical / Historical
Sylvia Shaw Judson (1897-1978) was a sculptor and writer active in Chicago, Illinois. Her work Bird Girl received popular attention after her death.
Sylvia Shaw Judson, who went by Sylvia Haskins in her personal life, was the daughter of prominent architect Howard Van Doren Shaw and Frances Shaw. She studied with Albin Polasek at the Art Institute of Chicago and went to Paris in 1920 to continue her studies under Antoine Bourdelle at the Academy Grande Chaumiere.
Judson's sculpture often depicts children and animals. Notable works include Little Gardener which was included in Rachel "Bunny" Mellon's design for the White House Rose Garden, and Bird Girl in Bonaventure Cemetery in Savannah, Georgia.
As an adult, Judson joined the Society of Friends and became an active participant in the church. She died in 1978 in Lake Forest, Illinois.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Sylvia Shaw Judson papers were donated by her daughter, Alice Judson Ryerson in 1979. The material microfilmed on reels 1490-1495 was initially lent to the Archives for microfilming by the artist's daughter and subsequently given as a gift.
Sculptors -- Illinois -- Chicago; Quaker women; Women artists; Women sculptors; Drawings
- Biographical Material, 1920-circa 1960; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 1
  Biographical / Historical
  Found are biographical sketches and resumes, and artwork by Sylvia Judson and by J. Stoyanvoitch. Of note is a painted sketch of Bird Girl which is unsigned.
  - Biographical Sketches and Resumes, 1936, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Painted Sketch, The Peasant Girl or Bird Girl, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sketches, Unsigned (Likely by Sylvia Judson), circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sketches of Sylvia Judson, by J. Stoyanvoitch, 1920-1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1920-1975; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Judson's correspondence primary relates to business and is with artists, foundries and studios, friends, galleries, institutions, and museums. Correspondents include Arden Gallery, Art Exhibition Galleries--Mandel Brothers, Art Institute of Chicago, Dayton Art Institute, Grace Enthof, Erkins Studios, John Asmussen and Sons, Albin Polasek, Mario Ubaldi, Ferruccio Vitale, Bernard Walsh, Helen Ware, The White House, Whitney Museum of American Art, Wheeler Williams, and William Zorach. Also found are typescripts of letters sent by Judson to her family while she was in Paris in the early 1920s.
  - Typescripts, Sylvia to Family (from Paris), 1920-1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General, circa 1920s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General, 1924-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General, 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General, 1960-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General, 1967-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General, 1970-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Writings and Notes, 1911-1963; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Found are writings by Judson including drafts of articles, lectures, speeches, early writings from her school days, and notes. Writings by others consist of reviews and criticisms of Judson's sculptures.
  - Articles, Lectures, and Speeches, 1939-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Early Writings, 1911-1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notes, on Sculptural Techniques and Services, circa 1920-1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Reviews and Criticisms, by Others, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Professional Activities Files, 1933-1968; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Scope and Contents
  Found are subject files regarding Judson's work as a sculptor, educator, and writer. Files may contain correspondence, printed material, business and financial records, research, photographs, and drafts of writings and notes.
  - Cairo, Egypt--Teaching File, 1962-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - For Gardens and Other Places, Clippings and Reviews, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Mary Dyer, circa 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19-24)
  - Roman Bronze Works (Foundry), 1933-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
  - The Quiet Eye, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27-29)
  - The Quiet Eye, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
- Personal Business Records, 1923-1975; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 2
  Found are account ledgers, contracts, and various invoices and receipts for the production and sale of sculpture.
  - Account Ledger, for Sculpture Receipts and Expenses, 1923-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Art Institute of Chicago, Rental Gallery Records, 1954-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Contracts, 1930-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Financial Records, from Publications, 1952-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Invoices and Receipts, 1955-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Lists of Buyers and Locations of Sculpture, circa 1950-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Price Lists and Expenses, Sculpture, circa 1950-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Royalty Payments, 1955-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Printed Material, 1913-1970s; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 2-3, 6
  Printed materials largely concern Judson's sculpture and include art related publications, clippings, exhibition material, and reproductions of works of art. Also found are published copies of books written by Judson, a copy of a book written by her mother and illustrated by Judson, and issues of The Lantern, Judson's high school literary magazine.
  - Art Periodicals and Publications, 1920s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14-18)
  - Book, Songs of a Baby's Day, By Frances Shaw, Illustrated by Sylvia Shaw, 1914; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Books, by Sylvia Judson, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, 1920s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1919-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1919-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - The Lantern, Westover School Literary Magazine, 1913-1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Reproductions of Works of Art, 1950s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Reproductions of Works of Art, Oversized, 1950s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Photographs, circa 1920s-circa 1970s; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 1.9 Linear feet Box 3-6, OVs 7-8, MGP1
  Photographs depict Sylvia Shaw Judson's sculpture and photos may be of the work in situ or in a studio. Some files may include photos of Judson or others with various sculpture. The file for Corwin & Noah includes an original drawing of the work by Judson. Also found here are 12 glass plate negatives.
  - 4-H Club, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Ancestor, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Animals, circa 1940-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9-13)
  - Apple Tree Children, circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Baptismal Boy and Girl, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Bird Girl or Peasant Girl, circa 1930-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Birds, 1930s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
  - Boy in Overalls, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Boy Reading, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Boy with Bird and Basin, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Corwin & Noah, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Dog and Boy, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Early Work, 1910s-1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Edison Building Relief, 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Fort San Antonio Abad, Plaque, 1923-1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Fountain Nude, circa 1950s-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Girl with Squirrel, circa 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Head and Ura, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Humans, 1950s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - L. F. Hospital Stone Sculpture, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Little Brother, circa 1920-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Little Gardener, 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Mary Dyer, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Merchild, 1930s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Naughty Fawn, 1930s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Nude for Lily Pond, circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Pamela, circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Portraits, 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Prima Vera, 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Raintree Fountain, 1950s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Religious Sculpture, 1930s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Seasons, 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Shepherd, 1920s-1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Sister Frances, 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Stunts, 1920s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Roosevelt Memorial Fountain, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Susie Playing Recorder, 1950s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Triton, circa 1940-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Violin, Norman Ross Friend of Ravinia Memorial, circa 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Young Woman, circa 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Negatives of Works of Art, 1920s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2-6)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, Oversized, circa 1920s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, Oversized, circa 1920s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 7)
  - Portfolio of Works of Art, Oversized, circa 1920s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 8)
  - Glass Plate Negatives, circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Item MGP1)